DAN KLEIN: Here's another idea.
An algorithm called simulated
annealing.
The idea is that you can escape local
maxima by not simply going
uphill all the time.
If you go uphill all the time, you have
this problem that if you're going
uphill, and then there's a little blip,
and then uphill again, you may
stop here and declare victory, right?
And if only you would take this tiny
step downhill, you could just resume
what you were doing before,
getting better and better.
And so what you do is you essentially
bounce around.
So here's the algorithm in pseudocode,
but here's the important idea about
this algorithm.
You have some current state, just
like any local search algorithm.
And you're going to look at the
successors, just like in any other
search algorithm.
The difference is you have this other
concept of a temperature, OK?
And the idea is when the temperature
is high, you're
bouncing around like crazy.
And essentially you're going to go to
a neighbor, whether it's better than
you or not.
So what you do is you pick a
random successor, right?
Not the best successor,
a random successor.
And you figure out, is it
better or worse than me?
If it's better than me, I'll take it.
If it's worse than me,
maybe I'll take it.
I'll take it when the
temperature is high.
And so the beginning, you're just kind
of bouncing around like crazy.
And as time goes on, you
change the temperature.
You lower it.
This is where the annealing comes,
in it's a physics analogy.
You lower the temperature, and you take
these downhill steps less and
less often.
But if you only one downhill step away
from making huge progress, you'll sit
there, you'll bounce
around for a while.
Eventually you'll escape
and continue going.
So it's kind of uphill, but kind of a
very caffeinated way of going uphill.
Simulated annealing.
Magic or not?
So here's a theoretical guarantee the
sure makes it look like magic.
The guarantee says this.
It says that if you run this forever,
keep in mind you will not actually run
this forever.
If you did run this forever, then you
would find that you spend more time at
certain places in the search
space than others.
And because of how the algorithm works,
you spend more time at higher
places on the mountain.
So essentially E here is
your fitness function.
If the fitness function is high, you'll
spend more time up there,
because it kind of takes you longer to
bounce your way out of a very high
point than a very low point.
As the temperature decreases, you
tend to get stuck where you are.
So in essence, you've got this beautiful
guarantee this says as T
goes to zero, then you will converge
to the optimal state.
And you will spend kind of infinitely
much time there.
That's great.
OK, is this interesting?
Well, it's certainly interesting.
Is it useful?
So it sounds like magic, and sometimes
simulated annealing can be very
powerful for escaping
mild local optima.
However, it is still the case that if
you are at a local optimum, and you
need to take 30 downhill steps to get
out, you kind of have to take 30
downhill steps to get out without
getting distracted and going back up
to where you came from.
And typically, taking 30 downhill steps
is unlikely in any problem at
any temperature.
And so really, there's this issue that
if you are in a very, very kind of
extreme local optimum where you have
to take many downhill steps to get
out, you're probably suck
there in practice.
Yes, if you ran this forever,
after a billion years you
would finally escape.
And then you would get to an even better
place for which it would take
you a trillion years to escape.
So in the limit you're going to the
right thing, but given that you don't
care about anything much beyond the
first hour, and certainly not much you
on the first million years, that
guarantee may not actually help you.
What people do in addition to this a
of bouncing around a little bit is
they think about what are called ridge
operators, which basically say one way
or another, if my search face looks like
this, and I'm standing here, I'm
just in trouble.
And so rather than actually hoping
that something like simulated
annealing will just happen to want to
go downhill for a very long time,
instead what you think about is, is
there a way to kind of move to a
completely different region of the
space where maybe I can move
from peak to peak.
These operators are called ridge
operators, because rather than kind of
going along the search problem,
they add new directions.